Dr. Karan Mittal: How does it influence our life? What are the different terms that our Shastras use, or what are… what was the perspective of a Rishi's while designing Jyotish and Vastu? That's the theme of today's class, and without much of an introduction, let's probably directly jump into
Dr. Karan Mittal: the theme, I'm just under a filter for sharing. Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Cape.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, in Indian Shastras, like, I don't know, there are 6 orthodox systems of Indian philosophy, like, there are the six systems of philosophy that kind of consider Vedas as the topmost, or their supreme guiding principle.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And out of that, one of the oldest one is the Vaisha Shikdarshan. I'll not get into the details of the Darshan, but how it aligns to our class, we'll try to focus there. Vaisha Shikh Darshan speaks about 9 rabbias.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rabia's basically…
Dr. Karan Mittal: in our simple understanding, like, we talk about Mahabhutas, the Panchamahutas, which we all, you know, offer water, fire, space, and air. Similarly, the Vaishi Darshan, which is the oldest version, speaks of nine gravyas. It keeps the five that we just opened, the Panchamutas constant, but then it adds four more gravyas into the picture, that is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That is direction, time, that is kala, manas, and.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, one of the foremost, or one of the most ancient Darshanas considered time and deisha, that is, dhik, that is Visha, as one of the grounding principles of our life, and
Dr. Karan Mittal: Other things that develop, other shastras that develop in our tradition, whether it's Ayurveda, whether it's yoga, basically draw their understanding of the world, or understanding of the universe from Vaisha Sheikh and Samhydration. So therefore, you'll see that in Ayurveda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Kala and deisha, that is, that is time, as well as deisha, that is geographical location, play a very important role.
Dr. Karan Mittal: whether it's the timing of medicine, whether it's, you know, plucking of medicines from the plants, whether it's processing it at a particular point of time, everything in Ayurveda, if you go into the intricate Ayurveda, has
Dr. Karan Mittal: times that are recommended by the Ayurveda charias, or by our rishis, whether it's Taraka Rishi, or Sushutrishi, or Bhagavad, they have recommended times for various, various procedures in Ayurveda, right? From growing the plant to the consumption of the medicine, everything has a particular time.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Similarly, Ayurveda also saw that, you know, a plant probably growing in the north of India, and the same plant growing probably in central India, showed different properties. Solid from a particular part of the world and another particular part of the world kind of had different propensities and properties, and it… the way it affected the body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Same thing applies for humans. Humans in certain parts of the world or certain parts of our country have different vicrutis, in the sense, different dosha imbalances and predominances. So, Ayurveda as a science of physical health.
Dr. Karan Mittal: saw this importance of kala, that is, time and disha, in our day-to-day lives. And it also said that when you misalign, or you are not able to align your lifestyle with the Kala or a Disha, diseases arise.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when we look at the physical science, definitely our understanding or our beliefs, kind of, when Vairdacharya tells us to take medicine at a particular time, we follow that principle.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you go to the spiritual side, if you go to the metaphysical side, we also know that, you know, chanting in Brahma Murata or Vanasarna in Brahma Murata at one particular place, one particular time, enhances our spiritual
Dr. Karan Mittal: potion, or enhances our switches are now.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But the problem statement of today's class, or probably the classes that follow, lies between these two principles. Physical dimensions, we believe that time, and even the modern science believes in that we have chronobiology, and we have so many other principles that kind of support that how body, or even in psychology, we know that different
Dr. Karan Mittal: days, or different seasons, or different age groups, we have different developmental traits that happen. So, as a physical science, or as a physical evolution, we definitely take the consideration of time and direction, or that is Disha in our life. Similarly, for
Dr. Karan Mittal: Our spiritual or metaphysical aspects of our life. We take that dimension into our consideration that we chant… try to chant at a particular period of time, we try to sit at a particular space, in a particular consciousness, to enhance our spiritual shadma.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But the problem statement is, between this physics and metaphysics, whatever other things that lie, we fail to consider the importance of time and space into these things. Whether it's our mental well-being, whether it's our material well-being, whether it's prosperity, whether it's our lifestyle, we fail to consider the importance of time and direction into these aspects of life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And this is the place.
Dr. Karan Mittal: This is the place where the signs of, or where the Shastra of Jokish and Vasco Panza do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Jyotish being the science of the Shastra of time, and Rastu mean being the chastra of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the space, or the direction of, and how to kind of finance it for our building. So, Rishi is kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: design these Shastras, or design these sciences, index sciences, in a way to kind of make the two Dhravyas that we spoke of, the Kalam and dhic, compatible to our well-being, compatible to our prosperity, compatible to our progress. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: That's where Jyotish and Vastu come. Of course, Jyotish and Vastu also give directions and also give injunctions on how to enhance your spiritual well-being by following those principles, as well as your physical well-being. So the kind of… the ripples of Jyotish and Vastu also flow into the physical health and also the metaphysical portion.
Dr. Karan Mittal: When Jyotish… if you go to write to the Vedic times, the pure Vedic times, like Veda, Tharva Veda, Yaja Veda, Jyotish was the science of time alignment. It was not the science of prediction.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It was… it was a Shasta that aligned different aspects of our life to the… to the aspects in the nature, whether it's planets, starts, seasons, or… or sunrise, sunset, day and night. So it kind of enhanced, or it kind of aligned the… the different aspects in one's life, whether it's studies, whether it's open construction of a new house, whether it's anything, anything, whether it's a yadda.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It started from Yogya, but the ripples, or the effects of it, spread into different walks of human life to align the cosmic timing with your personal goals. So that was Judish.
Dr. Karan Mittal: In the beginning, in the Vedic times. Of course, at a later stage, then the prediction, etc, also became an important aspect. But basically, the Vedic Jyotish was Muritha Shasta, that is, aligning auspicious time with auspicious things that a person does in life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: There were other two aspects, that is Ganita, which is the mathematical aspect of Jyotish, calculating the position of stars, planets, etc. And Pora and Falit, that is the Jyotish that we all know of, we all keep on hearing of, we all see in Star Reels.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and YouTube videos about it, which is about predictive astrology, that what will happen, why will it happen, and when will it happen? That's the Bora Peloticism.
Dr. Karan Mittal: But somewhere or the other, in the race of prediction, in the race of trying to predict with accuracy, we forget that Judith's one-third component is prediction, but the other one-third component is time alignment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: If the hora-Phalid part, even if it's not available, if you try to align your activities, your major decisions, with the Murata part, one-third of that positivity, or one-third of that hospitiousness that the universe bestows through planets, stars, nakshakras, etc, comes into my life.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So in the race of getting the accurate predictions and remedies, we forget that it's more about the science of alignment.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Rather than the signs of prediction, or the signs of claiming that I am 100% accurate as an instructor.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I keep… as an astrologer, I keep on speaking to different, you know, very famous astrologers, and of course, I belong to the Orthodox School of Jyotesha, so I speak to very Shastric astrologers who have studied Shastras for years and their lives, etc. And they always say that astrology is never about accuracy. It's not never about 100% accuracy. You cannot claim 100% accuracies. Even the Shastras speak it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when someone on a reel or on a social media claims that this is going to happen, that is going to happen, this is going to happen, and falls flat. Because astrology was never about 100% accuracy. It was about understanding what was possible.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Trying to align our decisions with the possibility, if at all both are contradictory, then doing various remedies to kind of
Dr. Karan Mittal: trying… align what's available in the… in the horoscope with the decision that you are trying to make. So, it was about aligning our decisions with what's kind of presented in your astrological chart. And even from the Upaya perspective, I was speaking to
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, I got an opportunity to interact with one great astrologer on…
Dr. Karan Mittal: He, he… basically, David Guruji, David Guruji is the one who, who has been instrumental in…
Dr. Karan Mittal: finding the Murata of consecration of Ayodian, or… so, one of the great astrologers in Denos today. So, so he sometimes
Dr. Karan Mittal: as Upayas gives mantra chanting, in the sense, you know, 1.25 lakhs of mantras to be chanted of a particular planet for a particular reason. And 1.25 lakh chanting of that mantra probably is approximately 200 human hours. Approximately 200 human hours. And still, sometimes, you know.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the results don't come in. So, when he was asked that, okay, you kind of described this, this, this is this, and nothing happened. So, even in the Upaya part.
Dr. Karan Mittal: via what Shastras prescribed, etc, have to be equally contradictory, or equally create an opposite
Dr. Karan Mittal: Equal and opposite force to the force of parabda that you have created in earlier lives.
Dr. Karan Mittal: doing one small remedy, doing one particular tot that is on social media, and saying that this will bring in money, this will solve all your problems. That's not how Shastas look at it. You have to create an equal opposite force to the Pradabdha in order to kind of nullify that Parabhdha. Just doing something small here and there can work, can enhance your positivity, or can enhance your perspective of looking at
Dr. Karan Mittal: That particular Shastra, but it's not something that's a short-shot alternative from Shastik perspective. So, Shastas speak about two things. Upayas are given because changing is possible. It doesn't speak about that if it is written in the horoscope, it is what… this is what is going to happen. And it also says that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Upayas are not like everything. Once you do upayas, you have to create an equal and opposite fold. Just doing a small donation, or a small japa, or a small tot will not solve the problem if your equally strong.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, it talks about this balanced perspective. You talk about balanced accuracy in prediction, and you also talk about a balanced approach to the buyers. Some people also get into this
Dr. Karan Mittal: habit of spending lakhs and lakhs and lakhs and doing various memories, deposits, etc. So that's also the Shastas kind of, kind of prohibit, that you cannot go into this kind of, maybe addiction to do buyers. So that's… that's about how Shastas look at it.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And coming to the Vasco Purushop, find it… coming up… coming to the directional aspect of it. We'll come to some application part at the end of this, but I'm just creating a framework right now. So, even astrologically, if we see… even from a Vasco perspective, when we see that
Dr. Karan Mittal: whenever you look at the geographical space, now for… for the definition of Wastu, anything with four, you know, closed
Dr. Karan Mittal: boundaries is considered a vastu. It could be a temple, it could be a house, it could be a factory, anything which has boundaries on the land is considered a vastru. Even the table that we're sitting on right now, you kind of watch this video, it's also a vast in some way or the other. So when you go to the micro level, it also is also about aligning the energy of the place where you're working.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So…
Dr. Karan Mittal: The planets that are spoken in astrology are also kind of, you know, the Shastras work on this principle of Yakin Deatha Bravande. What is there in the universe is in your body. So, the planets are placed in your body also, the planets are placed in the vastu, or the house that you live in also, and the planets are there placed in that universe.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, Vastu is basically… aligning that
Dr. Karan Mittal: Planet that is there working for you in your astrology, that is, like, in your body.
Dr. Karan Mittal: with the planet that you are staying, or the planet in the house, wherever the planet is placed in your particular house or factory, etc. Aligning when these both get aligned, depending upon your astrology, the placement of the planet here in the body, and the planet… the placement of the planet in the Vastu, then
Dr. Karan Mittal: the fruitful results, or the beneficial results of aspirin juice start coming in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So most of the times, you know, we either try to align the time, we try to align the direction, some people have, like, more wastuk prone, some people are more jutish prone, but the balance lies where we align the internal planet, that is self-work, that is conscious work, as the title of the slide, or this lecture is.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the planet in the house, that is the Vastu, and the planet in the universe, that is the astrology. When these three start getting aligning, the full potential of a particular person starts releasing, or starts… starts getting…
Dr. Karan Mittal: and the world. So that's the aspect of WASCU, and WASCU kind of places all these nine planets in different, different directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Apart from the planets, there are also placement of different devtas. So, depending upon, like, like, suppose
Dr. Karan Mittal: Suppose I, I, I am related to teaching.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And the planet for teaching is Jupiter, so… so… and the placement of Vastu is… is kind of in… for Jupiter, is in the northeast corner of the house.
Dr. Karan Mittal: studying in the Northeast, or lecturing in the Northeast, cleaning up the Northeast, okay, doing some Guru Japa, etc. We'll start aligning the Jupiter planet for me, my internal consciousness, the Vaspoon, and the Japa will also
Dr. Karan Mittal: get the benedictions of the Jupiter as a planet, and it will start aligning the potential of that teacher.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, just for an example, how Vasco kind of also places the five elements that we've… that we spoke, into different, different directions. So, the northeast, or the Ishanyam, is the direction of water.
Dr. Karan Mittal: It is the direction of spirituality, it's the direction… because Jupiter is also placed over there, so it's the direction of spirituality also. So, basically, northeast, because it is water, it is Jupiter, it is about
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Devta over there is Ish, that is Shiva, it's all about clarity, it's all about focus, it's all about meditation, it's all about, spirituality. So when the north… when you want to do a meditation, definitely the zone will be northeast, because it will enhance all these qualities.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For you. In the Agnir, or in the southeast, is the zone of fire element. So, definitely.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Ashastras, or you might have heard it also, the kitchen used to be in Southeast, because when the fire is being lit for cooking every day, the fire element of… of the southeast will promote
Dr. Karan Mittal: the fire element of that cat's stove. Supposedly, the fire element, if the kitchen is in northeast, then definitely water and fire are anti-elements. They will contradict each other. So that's how our rishis, or our seers, kind of conceptualize it. They placed
Dr. Karan Mittal: And all these placements also have a reason. It's like there are shlopas and Vedas and Nishas which make these placements, which their goes where. It's not that someone has just created these placements. Now, Southwest is basically Earth element. It's all about groundedness, it's about heaviness, it's about authority. So, definitely, the owner of the house needs to
Dr. Karan Mittal: sit, sleep, or the owner of the office needs to have his cabin in the southwest, because it gives that… it gives them that authority, that groundedness. If supposedly some worker or some… some… some servant starts staying in the southwest, she will start becoming authoritative as per hospital instance. Or… or supposedly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: there's a child in the house who's docile, passive, depressed, okay? And… and…
Dr. Karan Mittal: I have made his bedroom in the Northeast. Now, Northeast is, again, a direction of calmness, spirituality, passivity, you know, going deep inside. Will that direction promote the well-being of that particular person? Because that person is already in Tamogur now, because of his depression at that time. Now you're enhancing
Dr. Karan Mittal: the passivity or the docility by putting him in the Northeast. So Basu kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: aligns the… the need of a person with the space, or with the direction, or with the properties of that direction. Similarly, Northwest is for air, so all the movements of the air that… or wind, everything related to movement is somewhere in the northwest. So.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, supposedly, if a person is very hyperactive.
Dr. Karan Mittal: and I place him in… place him in either southeast or in northwest, the hyperactivity will increase, because wind will promote the hyperactivity in some way, fire will promote hunger and aggression in some other way, so the hyperactivity will increase, because the vastly is not getting aligning… is not aligning to the inner consciousness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And similarly, the center, or the Brahmastan, is about Hapasha, or ether. It kind of promotes space, it promotes, it promotes, you know, productivity. So, it is a place where all the direction meet, and it is the center point of the
Dr. Karan Mittal: energetic confluence of all the directions. So it's all about generation, potential, creativity, space, farsightedness, that's the Brahmistan.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And if you go, like, I've just added 3 points, and it's like, if you go from environmental, psychology, and neuroarchitecture perspective, what… what…
Dr. Karan Mittal: what we speak about elements, etc. So, it's always said that when you're studying or doing some work, your eyes should… in Moscow, it's said that you should have, like, there shouldn't be a wall right in front of your space, and there should be a chair or something that supports your back, because… because…
Dr. Karan Mittal: the support at your back is kind of the… is kind of earth element, and the space that you're seeing, a far-sighted reach, is ether element, or is a space element. Now, if you come from an environmental psychological perspective, that promotes a safety. Your brain senses safety, because once you have a support at your back.
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know that nothing is going… coming from that. And when you're able to see far.
Dr. Karan Mittal: from the place where you're, where you are sitting, you can also judge if some danger, etc, is coming. So the brain senses it. It is called as a prospect refuge theory. The brain senses it, and brain senses that safety, and is able to then
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of divert that area of the brain that is always trying to sense danger into something productive that level. And similarly, the vascular peaks. There should be earth element at your back, and there should be other element in front of you when you're doing some work to promote… to promote productivity.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Similarly, an open space, or an empty space in the center of the house kind of gives us this feel that the house is open, and there's air, and there's volume in the house, and there's no congestion, etc. So it kind of promotes a happiness, or promotes a peaceful environment in the house, and that's called as the cathedral effect. So, the principles of environmental psychology, somewhere or the other, or neuroarchitecture, somewhere
Dr. Karan Mittal: or the other align with what was the steps. It's basic human understanding that our rishis have given in form of Shastras, in form of
Dr. Karan Mittal: And it's in form of elements.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So… So sometimes we have different issues, like, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I always say that the same flat that is in a, you know, in Mumbai and in Metropolitan City, there's a flat that, you know, runs for different, like, maybe multiple floors, 50, 60, 100 floors. And, you know, every person who's living in those 100 flats or 80 flats have different, different
Dr. Karan Mittal: effects of the same mask, because for those 100 flats in one series, the VASCU is the same, approximately the same, with some inner changes. But every flat, even one single flat, once you move into a flat, that flat will affect different members of the house differently.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, is Vastu only the thing? No. The personal astrology, or the personal tala of the person also matters, and also the personal consciousness, or the inner Anthrakaran, what we call inner shasis, also matters. So, aligning all these three things, as I said, that aggressive
Dr. Karan Mittal: child kind of sleeping in southeast, automatically the accretion will increase. But the docile child, or the passive child, it goes in the southeast.
Dr. Karan Mittal: fire element will enhance the activity in the child, and it will try to neutralize that hostility, or the passivity of the child. So, the inner consciousness, the Vaspu, and the astrology, kind of aligning with each other gives the best results.
Dr. Karan Mittal: For example, I've just taken this example where BAS2 and this gets aligned.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, so, Surya, in, in, of course, in modern medicine also, we, we…
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, in infectious diseases, wards, etc, there is importance of sunlight, okay? Because if sunlight somewhere or the other neutralizes many things. And also, from a psychological perspective, getting adequate sunlight is good for mental well-being. That's why countries where sunlight is not seen for
Dr. Karan Mittal: months and days together, weeks together, the chances of… that's the seasonal depression that people get. They feel depressed when sunlight is not visible, and that's what Vastu also echoes. Vastu kind of mandates the necessity
Dr. Karan Mittal: of sunlight in every house, and that's why it spoke about, you know, having yeast open, so that early morning sunlight enters, and it kind of made the sun, the Arogyakarata, the health promoter, because
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because sun, as per astrology, is also Arubyataraka, and coming of sunlight early in the morning in the house also promotes mental and physical well-being. But at the same time, if you go, and if you see Arushis, they said that south should be closed, because sun usually, in India, goes from east to south, and then sets in the west.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, when the south is open, or there are too many windows in the south, the aggressive sunlight of the afternoon, okay, usually comes into the house, heats up the house. So, Rishi spoke about closing the south and the southwest, and they always prescribe that the early morning general sunlight of the
Dr. Karan Mittal: east or southeast should be coming into the house, because that's around until 10 a.m, and after that, the south and the southwest needs to be closed. So they saw that the moment of the sun
Dr. Karan Mittal: the aggressive, or the intensity of the sunlight, sun being the health promoter, and then they prescribe that in Vasu that the east needs to do.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So now, supposedly, if a person is going through his Sandasha, and Sundasha is also about recognition, fame, power, etc, but he stays in the house where there is… there is absence of sunlight, or the sunlight doesn't come in, or the east direction is completely closed, completely cluttered.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Also, it doesn't get exposure, because you're sitting in a metro… staying in a metropolitan city, there's hardly any exposure to sunlight because of coal, buildings, etc. Then, this dasha, which is supposed to bring in that fame, recognition, etc, will not show its full effects, because sunlight is missing
Dr. Karan Mittal: as a physical touch also. It's also missing as a vastu principle. So, though the horoscope is showing that in this, the Shada person will get fame recognition, etc, he will get it, because astrology is saying, but the intensity of that fame recognition, etc, will reduce. And same thing will apply for health.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, if a person who has poor health and doesn't get exposure to sunlight, or because of the yeast being blocked, it will start affecting his health.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Same thing what I gave as an example of the teacher. So, a teacher, basically, from astrological principle is Jupiter Planet, Guru Planet, or Jupiter is Devtra Guru.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the teacher of the dev tasks.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And a teacher, if the northeast area of the house, which is the area of Jupiter, is cluttered, is blocked, has some anti-element into it, it will surely affect the profession of the teacher, first, from the undercurrent perspective, because the bus is not aligning with the profession.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And also, when the Guru Dasha starts, and the time when he should
Dr. Karan Mittal: move ahead in this teaching field, spirituality, etc. also, because the Northeast's blackboard is corrupted. It will not allow that to happen to its fullest extent. So, it's not just about Paso alone, it's not just about Judish, and it's not just about Antikar and Quran. It's the three together that start enhancing one's credential.
Dr. Karan Mittal: solve them.
Dr. Karan Mittal: as… as a… as a takeaway, like, as a takeaway from the Disha perspective, or the Vastri perspective, and our Vastu Shastri Ghanvas are very clear about it, if one needs, like.
Dr. Karan Mittal: like, usually there's a lack of clarity in someone's life about what problem exactly is happening at how, there are fights happening at the house, people are confused about what career, what marriage, what studies to do, etc. So somewhere or the other, the mental
Dr. Karan Mittal: lack of mental clarity is foremost, or maybe the starting principle of many problems, whether it's fights or wrong decisions, etc. So, Shastras are very clear about the first and the foremost thing that a person should do to kind of align the desha, or the vastal, with
Dr. Karan Mittal: one's life is, to clear the Northeast, to make the Northeast as clean as possible, as bright as possible, with as much as wind flow as possible, because once Northeast starts enhancing.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Jupiter starts elancing, the spirituality, the mental clarity starts announcing, and automatically, the decisions that were probably foggy earlier, somewhere or the other, the clarity comes in.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And similarly.
Dr. Karan Mittal: we saw the five elements and the directions. Seeing which area of your life, or which area in the family is somewhere problematic. Is it the health of the person, of the family members? Is it the career? Is it studies, etc.
Dr. Karan Mittal: kind of trying to see if which room in the bathroom, or in the house, is kind of not aligning with what it is meant for. So, supposedly the kitchen is in the northeast, okay, probably then the health, or the fire element of the house is not
Dr. Karan Mittal: not… not aligned with the Vasu. So somewhere or the other, health will start getting affected. If the bedroom… if the person who's having the problem, suppose the problem is depression, where is the pro… where is the bedroom?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Of that particular individual. Seeing all these things and trying to see if the zone matches the characteristics of the room that is there, and the characteristics of a person
Dr. Karan Mittal: who's sleeping or staying in that room. If a depressed person is definitely seeing everything in Northeast, then definitely the depression needs… will get enhanced, and trying to see if
Dr. Karan Mittal: that alignment or misalignment exists in the life of that particular member of the house. So these are the two things that you can try, probably, and trust me, Ishania clearing… clearing the northeast area of the house starts showing results in 7 to 10 days. Like, of course, I don't… I don't over-claim it, but definitely something starts moving.
Dr. Karan Mittal: on this. That's what I spoke of.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. So, for now, for now, for this, for today, it's…
Dr. Karan Mittal: It's about aligning the anthatarand, your inner consciousness, the jutisha, and the Vaspu together for the personal benefits, or for enhancement of your prosperity, material benefits, virtuality, etc. It's never stand alone in Ashastis.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Thank you. Over to Govind Prabhu.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you, Karanji.
GOVINDA Das: For presenting very succinctly. One of the most important parts you mentioned about
GOVINDA Das: whether Vastu, specifically in regards to Jyoteshe Shastra, It's about alignment.
GOVINDA Das: Other than… instead of predictability.
GOVINDA Das: But what do we do? We focus more on predictability, rather than… Aligning with the time.
GOVINDA Das: In the Raman, we see… the Sharath Maharaj.
GOVINDA Das: who was organizing the greatest function of coronating Lord Ramachandra.
GOVINDA Das: And Lord Ramachandra… It's about to be coronated.
GOVINDA Das: And the muhurta was decided by the many rishis in the Sharat Maharaj's place.
GOVINDA Das: Then the question is raised… Why?
GOVINDA Das: Even… A day after the Muharta was arranged, the coronation did not happen.
GOVINDA Das: Where did the riches fail?
GOVINDA Das: Where did the Shrat Maharaj fail?
GOVINDA Das: While Lord Ramachandra had to go to the forest.
GOVINDA Das: One may say, because it was his plan. Plan? Yes.
GOVINDA Das: That is the divine perspective.
GOVINDA Das: Then if it was the divine perspective, then what is the point of the rishis organizing the Murta?
GOVINDA Das: Not one astrologer, not two astrologers, must have been many. Still, it failed.
GOVINDA Das: Because, as Dr. Karan was mentioning, If you study…
GOVINDA Das: It was alignment of the time.
GOVINDA Das: not simply hoping everything will go nicely. Dasharat Maharaj had a cognitive bias. He had the bias of doing it as early as possible.
GOVINDA Das: Before it could be stopped by Kaikai's father, Kaikai's uncle, Right in Kaikai herself.
GOVINDA Das: Because he had given the Varadhan.
GOVINDA Das: So, when there is a prateksha current, the muhurstas will not function. It does not matter how best the Murta is.
GOVINDA Das: Right, so therefore, alignment instead of… Creating a predictable reality.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, when we study, there are two classes of people that defy the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: But I… They defy the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: And for specifically those who are practicing, Dharmic tradition.
GOVINDA Das: who defies… one is the hardcore materialistic people. They defy the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: Through their hard labor, certainly they create certain Material convenience.
GOVINDA Das: The vehicles are created, you know, communication is created, medicines are created, But if you study.
GOVINDA Das: We are not discussing philosophy here, we are discussing reality here.
GOVINDA Das: If you study the quality of life, what was experienced by
GOVINDA Das: Those who lived primitively, not chose to live poorly.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they were… their resources were very less.
GOVINDA Das: They had much better mental… stable life. May not be so physically healthy, but mental stability was extremely higher.
GOVINDA Das: Because they did not defy the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: They may not have the complete picture about how the laws function.
GOVINDA Das: That requires much more learning and education.
GOVINDA Das: And the second class of people, those who defy the laws of life, Are they unevolved spiritualists?
GOVINDA Das: Right? They defy the laws of God in the name of God.
GOVINDA Das: It's very important to understand.
GOVINDA Das: Right, when we defy the laws of life.
GOVINDA Das: The advancement of the civilization is visible for us. We can see it.
GOVINDA Das: But the experience of life is also visible for us.
GOVINDA Das: When you go and talk to every individual.
GOVINDA Das: Separate from the, you know, IPL victory, the political victory, all that, keep aside.
GOVINDA Das: When you ask a person to person about their stability.
GOVINDA Das: We will come to know, oh my god, there is so much of poverty in regards to mental health and intellectual health.
GOVINDA Das: We're talking Prataksha Pramana. Why?
GOVINDA Das: Because the laws of life have been defied royally.
GOVINDA Das: And what does Vastu and Jyotisha Shastra do?
GOVINDA Das: They are not law books.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they are observant of the reality.
GOVINDA Das: as… as Karan was showing about the certain slides, The time alignment.
GOVINDA Das: right, in the Ayurved, for example, eating
GOVINDA Das: the muli, what do you call it? Roots.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: So, there are certain write-ups which explain which grains to be eaten on which time. Something which is very good in the morning.
GOVINDA Das: It is not necessarily good in the evening.
GOVINDA Das: These rules are completely defied by the living entities.
GOVINDA Das: For example, when a farmer goes in the morning hours.
GOVINDA Das: You know, before 6 o'clock, now you do not see farmers do that.
GOVINDA Das: Because they do not go before the sun is risen, Health-wise, they're extremely pained.
GOVINDA Das: It's a gruesome task, because you begin your day at the wrong time.
GOVINDA Das: Seeing that, Gives us very clear understanding.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, when we… when we understand this principle of defying the life.
GOVINDA Das: In the Bhagavad Gita, again, we have quoted this many times.
GOVINDA Das: Krishna makes it very clear in the Bhagavad Gita, java.
GOVINDA Das: What does he say? He says, my dear Arjun.
GOVINDA Das: I do not interfere into the pious and impious activities of the living entities.
GOVINDA Das: And why do the living entities suffer? They're bewildered? Because…
GOVINDA Das: Their knowledge is covered by ignorance.
GOVINDA Das: Now there is limitless facility, right, to… to… to gain knowledge.
GOVINDA Das: The modern system has provided, especially this new AI technology, Has made people extremely informative.
GOVINDA Das: But Vastu and Jyotes Shastra are not an informative science.
GOVINDA Das: There, basically, makes you aware, alert, experience it.
GOVINDA Das: Like, one of the students, after passing his… Compless exam.
GOVINDA Das: He came to Ganga, Ganga Devi, Mother Ganga.
GOVINDA Das: And he said, I have come here not to ask anything, but to offer gratitude, because in my difficult times, nobody stood by me.
GOVINDA Das: But when I would come to the bank of Ganga Devi, Non-namata.
GOVINDA Das: Nadi… What happened? He said, I would experience complete peace. That is Vastu.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, In this Shimat Bhagavatam, 5th Kanto, The description of Bharat
GOVINDA Das: Very interesting. The description of Bharat is not based upon the royalties or the sages.
GOVINDA Das: Shukadeya Goswami himself, when he's describing the Bharat Bhumi, how does it define… how do you know what is Bharat?
GOVINDA Das: The politicians, the peacemaker, they say, oh, this is the land of Gandhi and Buddha.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: This is the land of Gandhi, Buddha, Mahavir, some other… they can't take the names of Krishna and Lord Ramachandra.
GOVINDA Das: But what does the Bhagavatam define when it defines the Bharat?
GOVINDA Das: It's extremely interesting and important to understand.
GOVINDA Das: Suguthya Gursami defines Bharat by the collection of rivers, not swimming pool.
Raj K: Mountains and rivers.
GOVINDA Das: You know, it defines by the collection of rivers.
GOVINDA Das: And then it describes the collection of mountains.
Raj K: That's it.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When there are collection of mountains and rivers, that is the definition of bar earth.
GOVINDA Das: And that collection of rivers and mountains, nobody can share their names.
GOVINDA Das: Sindhu Nadi, which is flowing in the… the artificial Pakistan, is still Sindhu Nadi.
GOVINDA Das: They cannot change the Himalayan mountains, the Vindya Mountains.
GOVINDA Das: They do not change.
GOVINDA Das: What is it? It is a description of Vastu.
GOVINDA Das: Right, Chanaki Panditan Artha Shastra explains…
GOVINDA Das: It says, those who do not make their civilization on the bank of the river, Have no civilization.
GOVINDA Das: Escapeur, you know, when we little observe, by observing this, we can understand The…
GOVINDA Das: so-called pious Indians are good at rituals.
GOVINDA Das: We do the rituals, right?
GOVINDA Das: But our ingredients are also a Vastu, Prana, hina.
GOVINDA Das: If it is… if it is when you're doing some puja, imagine your milk is coming from a cow.
GOVINDA Das: Which has been slaughtered.
GOVINDA Das: Usme prana kise hoga, how there is prana? Why can't we connect this symbol?
GOVINDA Das: Devotion does not need ingredients.
GOVINDA Das: But if we need ingredients, then we need to have some kind of…
GOVINDA Das: Awareness, okay, this milk cannot be offered.
GOVINDA Das: dood haine.
GOVINDA Das: How will it work? Imagine we are offering Abhisheikh to the DTE, Vasti ki bhat kar ramaya, devotion ki bhi bhat nahi kara.
GOVINDA Das: That milk, which is procured from those cows, Which are slaughtered.
GOVINDA Das: They've been used as a productive thing. If they're not productive, drop them down.
GOVINDA Das: How will it benefit If I do not see sunrise.
GOVINDA Das: or if I do not get connected to sun, therefore, every Bharatiya, for that matter.
GOVINDA Das: It didn't matter, Brahmanak, Kshatriya, Vaisha, Shudra.
GOVINDA Das: He offered water to Suryadev, extremely secular.
GOVINDA Das: We call it as… The real terminology is Dharmic.
GOVINDA Das: Karte nahia.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When we are not connected to Surya, and we know very clearly, depression…
GOVINDA Das: In the land of Europe, when the sun is not there, seasonal depression, as Dr. Karan called, is a reality. Just Google it.
GOVINDA Das: Right.
GOVINDA Das: And we are not connected to that sun, even though we have plenty of sunlight.
GOVINDA Das: That is one of the core principles of Vastu Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: Eastern direction may. Suri Prakash kelei, Dharvaja kolo.
GOVINDA Das: 98% of the Hindus will not know.
GOVINDA Das: Then raising the question, why, of driving all this kind of spiritual rituals, knowledge, why we are so uncivilized in regards to our civic behavior?
GOVINDA Das: Alright, now it is wherever you go.
GOVINDA Das: Like, Indians are, whether they're at the airport, whether they're going to some trip
GOVINDA Das: It is increasing, because the money is there, money is being earned, but that money has no vastu. It is haunted by the ghostly mindset.
GOVINDA Das: Lakshmi is called a chanchil in the hands of those people who do not know how to handle it.
GOVINDA Das: It's like ghost haunting.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, Therefore, the entire Vastu, or Jyotesha Shastra, You know, it explains…
GOVINDA Das: Generally, people think that we build homes.
GOVINDA Das: Home build people. Therefore, it is called as a graha.
GOVINDA Das: Graham means what? Graha means to consume.
GOVINDA Das: Graham means to capture.
GOVINDA Das: Graha means to influence.
GOVINDA Das: Alright.
GOVINDA Das: So, therefore, It is a circular logic.
GOVINDA Das: We build the homes, and homes build us.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, it is explained, the prana shakti, whether in your objective reality.
GOVINDA Das: Or in your subjective reality. In one sense, home is like an objective reality.
GOVINDA Das: visible.
GOVINDA Das: It can be understood what kind of design it has.
GOVINDA Das: We can see the directions.
GOVINDA Das: We can see how the sunlight is there.
GOVINDA Das: Any ordinary person, if they enter into a home, not a building.
GOVINDA Das: When you enter into home, it is very easy to recognize there is some
GOVINDA Das: Problem in the flow of the energy.
GOVINDA Das: Similarly, there is a prana in the living entity also.
GOVINDA Das: And what does Jyotish Shastra, Vastu Shastra, Yoga Shastra, they do, their only purpose
GOVINDA Das: is to enhance our Prana Shakti to such an extent in the Mahabharat. It is explained very interesting.
Raj K: If there is some energy that was negative or positive.
GOVINDA Das: in the… in the Mahabharata that is explained.
GOVINDA Das: When someone… you see elderly person, Elder to you, my age, by character, by experience.
GOVINDA Das: When you do not offer obeisances to them, pagilak, Gujaratime pagayak, Right?
GOVINDA Das: Piper, the Paidaroo.
GOVINDA Das: Right? When they fail to offer their obeisances to their superiors, Mahabharat says the prana is coming out.
GOVINDA Das: JC punko pranam karte ho ki akip prana firstander chali jati, your prana goes back.
GOVINDA Das: Simple, simple act of… Respecting the superior gives rise to a limitless experience of Pranas Shakti.
GOVINDA Das: Archkal Pete Pur, right? Thaktapana.
GOVINDA Das: That is lost. These are simple, simple, ordinary things.
GOVINDA Das: They are not complex. Yes, if you want complex science, it is there.
GOVINDA Das: You know, Karan is conducting Friday's course on this subject.
GOVINDA Das: You know, much more deeper, practically applicable.
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, a human being does not live independent of his mind, his space, and his prana.
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, the physical space, what does it create? It creates home's environment.
GOVINDA Das: And the psychological conditioning creates a mind's environment.
GOVINDA Das: And the cosmic timing, the astrology and Jyotish Shastra, what does it do? It creates a harmony between our space and the cosmic space. Waha, coherency, okay, there will be a coherency between the
GOVINDA Das: Between the individual space and the collective space, you will not be resisting.
GOVINDA Das: Right? The resistance is the cause of disease.
GOVINDA Das: Resistance is the cause of mental problem.
GOVINDA Das: But if that resistance is not there, natural flow is there, just like when somebody knows swimming, and swimming along with the current.
GOVINDA Das: Then the swimming doesn't exist.
GOVINDA Das: You're simply flowing along with the water.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: Therefore, What does it do?
GOVINDA Das: The… the modern psychology also mentions
GOVINDA Das: In fact, even in the architect designing.
GOVINDA Das: If there is too much of space, it is scary.
GOVINDA Das: If you are staying In the place where there is density of population, That is also painfully suffocating.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Therefore, clutter, what does it do?
GOVINDA Das: It increases a cognitive load, aapke man mein load bad jyata thai.
GOVINDA Das: or Prakash, Surya Prakash, the sunlight.
GOVINDA Das: is one of the main reasons sunlight and moon rays, they have the… they have the power to increase the mood. In fact, I was asking somebody.
GOVINDA Das: If you study our, our Gurukul system.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the holiday was not on Sunday.
GOVINDA Das: The holiday was during Purunima, and Amuassaya.
GOVINDA Das: Because Sunday is the day, it is the day of Surya.
GOVINDA Das: It is the day of action.
GOVINDA Das: Right? The peaceful day, much more sobering and much more enjoying day is Monday and Friday, because Monday is the day of moon.
GOVINDA Das: Friday is the day of… You know, pleasure.
GOVINDA Das: So, natural light And natural days, what do they do? They create proper mood.
GOVINDA Das: And space, height, When you see the sky, when you don't get to see the sky.
GOVINDA Das: The thinking of the people shrinks more and more.
GOVINDA Das: I heard one army officer made an interesting comment. I don't think he must have read any Shastra.
GOVINDA Das: In a very, very profound point he made.
GOVINDA Das: Because these soldiers, they are not in a small place. They're in the open space. They are… they are conquering the mountains.
GOVINDA Das: You know, they are into the sky.
GOVINDA Das: Imagine this man without knowing he experienced the concept of Nishkama karma.
GOVINDA Das: Very, very beautifully put. He said, when you experience fallah in the karma itself.
GOVINDA Das: When you experience fruit in the karma itself, he said you are liberated.
GOVINDA Das: Think about it. In the Bhagavatam.
GOVINDA Das: When Krishna, after meeting the gopis, He disappeared from them.
GOVINDA Das: And before he let them go back to their home.
GOVINDA Das: Krishna spoke to the gopis, he said, I have nothing to offer to you.
GOVINDA Das: Be satisfied with your own devotional service.
GOVINDA Das: Imagine, that is more poetic, more devotional.
GOVINDA Das: more scholarly, more Rasayukta, but the same thing was spoken by an army soldier, able to say when your karma itself becomes your Fala.
GOVINDA Das: What is that? That is the broader thinking.
GOVINDA Das: Right?
GOVINDA Das: And therefore, in the Bharatiya Sanskrati, One of the greatest tragedy.
GOVINDA Das: We see both men and women
GOVINDA Das: One of the greatest tragedies in the modern world, everyone wears black t-shirt.
GOVINDA Das: Black t-shirt, black pant, black t-shirt, black pant.
GOVINDA Das: Colors impact emotional state.
GOVINDA Das: go to Rajasthan, even though it's a desert, varieties of turbines were there.
GOVINDA Das: Right? So, therefore, understanding this more deeper, I just connected to the principle.
GOVINDA Das: When we connect it to the strategy of Vastu, and Jyotesha… What does it do?
GOVINDA Das: It makes us experience Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita, very profound.
GOVINDA Das: What does Krishna say? He says, I am the ability in man.
GOVINDA Das: I am the strength of the strong.
GOVINDA Das: And I'm the intelligence of the intelligent.
GOVINDA Das: Right? Strength of the strong.
GOVINDA Das: If somebody experiences strength, ability.
GOVINDA Das: That is not ego, that is a representation of God only, and therefore laws of God laws of Shastra…
GOVINDA Das: Give us greater connection to… Lord.
GOVINDA Das: than the so-called imagination of our connection to God.
GOVINDA Das: Thank you Any questions or comments, we can take 5-10 minutes.
Raj K: Which questions can you open it?
Sattvastha Ventures: Yeah, so, we have a question from Sanjay Shetirji.
Sattvastha Ventures: He's asking, Prabhuji, are these rules applicable even in Kaliog?
Sattvastha Ventures: Of respecting by touching feet of elders.
GOVINDA Das: What is that?
Sattvastha Ventures: Are these rules applicable even in Kaliog?
Sattvastha Ventures: Respecting… By touching feet of elders.
GOVINDA Das: Even the Rakshasa world, when Bali Maharaj…
GOVINDA Das: You know, when Bali Maharaj was not able to actually offer Obed Senses to Wamandev, he says, I simply offered my obedience in my mind, and see the benediction.
GOVINDA Das: Right? If it is… when you are inside your home.
GOVINDA Das: There is no harm in doing it. If you are living in the so-called proud world, it may be embarrassing, but at least in the mind.
GOVINDA Das: Being aware, being conscious of that.
GOVINDA Das: Because Yuga… Again, the concept of yoga is extremely relative.
GOVINDA Das: You know, the open issue, they talk about laws of life, it doesn't matter. The laws of life
GOVINDA Das: You drank water in Saty Yuga, you're drinking water now also, and the role of the water is to quench your thirst.
GOVINDA Das: So, the laws of life does not change because yugas change. They continue to remain. The process may differ.
GOVINDA Das: But the rule does not change.
Sattvastha Ventures: And, there is, one more question. Does it mean we should not wear black?
GOVINDA Das: Black is to attract all the dark energy you have seen in the building, they put a dark cloth so that all the black energy can be attracted, so you are simply attracting the dark energy.
GOVINDA Das: You know? Karan, you want to add something more about black?
Raj K: Hey, yay.
Dr. Karan Mittal: the Orthodox Memanza scholars also prohibit wearing black in any
Dr. Karan Mittal: any of the situations. So yes, there is a… there is… of course, then black also promotes other things. There's influence of different planets that increases, but yes, it should be avoided as per traditional scholars.
Sattvastha Ventures: So anyone have any other questions?
Sattvastha Ventures: So, yes, we have one more question, from, like, in Panji. What about white for married women?
Sattvastha Ventures: That seems to be a device against 2.
GOVINDA Das: Karan, you can answer. I'll add more.
GOVINDA Das: Karan?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes, boogie.
Dr. Karan Mittal: I'll just read the question. What about white for married women? That seems to be advised against, too. Yes, different colors have been advised for different phases of life, different, occasions, different intentions. So, different phases of life, you know, different colors are prescribed and prohibited.
Dr. Karan Mittal: And yes, but of course, these, colors also are very sociocultural. Different, civilizations and different socioculturally colors, like, in some civilizations, black is the color of moan, some white is the color of moaning. So usually, there are strict injunctions about these
Dr. Karan Mittal: you know, extreme colors, black and white. So yes, answering Rikenji Patel, yes, white is advised for married women in general. Yeah.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Because it's a color of mourning, as per certain belief systems.
GOVINDA Das: What do you, what do you, what do you say?
Dr. Karan Mittal: Sorry, Bruji.
GOVINDA Das: What do you say, last part?
Dr. Karan Mittal: In some… in sociocultural development, it's a color of mourning. So, color recommendations just don't come from Shasta, it's also a sociocultural evolution. So, in most of the traditions, yes, white is prohibited. Pure white, full white is prohibited, for people who symbolize auspiciousness.
Dr. Karan Mittal: USB.
GOVINDA Das: In Kerala, they have, no, the, like, a cream yellow, white.
GOVINDA Das: like, so, but that's the golden border, is there.
GOVINDA Das: Pure, pure complete white is not recommended when you come to worship the Lord.
GOVINDA Das: You know, colorful cloths are recommended.
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, extremes, Ruji, extremes are prohibited. Of course, the shades between, even in Wasco, if you go to see, extreme colors are prohibited in directions, but shades between, kind of, are still prescribed for different directions. Yeah, so black is a prohibited color in WASCU also, for any of the directions.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes. There's a question, but in Simantu Nayana, ceremony Garmini Mata is expected to wear black.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Wbg,
Dr. Karan Mittal: Would you like to shed any light? In my understanding, Simantonayana… see, you'll have to also see what is the intention of that particular sanskara. Accordingly, it changes. Like, Simantonayana is all about protection, and is all about creating bounties, or kind of…
Dr. Karan Mittal: how to overcome the threshold or the boundary. So, for that, an aggressive pillar is probably needed also. So, intentions also matter. Like, same in South India, black pillars were born when Murugan worships, etc, happened. So, depending on the deity, occasion, age, all these things, description change.
Dr. Karan Mittal: There's a question that Dr. Curran suggested kitchen should be in Southeast, but if kitchen is in Northwest, then what shall we do? Northwest is the secondary direction for kitchen, as per WASCO, so Northwest kitchen is not a big problem. It's not a problem at all, not a big…
Dr. Karan Mittal: So, sure.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are there
Dr. Karan Mittal: Are there any practical remedies to correct mistakes in Wasco? I mean that most homes are planned before children are born. Yes, there are. That's what Shastras also have propounded. There are practical remedies, there are practical intentional remedies, there are practical, ritualistic remedies. Yeah, there are many remedies for different, different nushas.
GOVINDA Das: Yeah, we'll stop here.
Dr. Karan Mittal: Yes.
Sattvastha Ventures: Yes, so… Thank you, Yvonne, for joining, and if you want to take any further questions and
Sattvastha Ventures: Consultation, you can just,
Sattvastha Ventures: Give a message to us on the mail or WhatsApp group that you're part of.
Sattvastha Ventures: Thank you. Thank you for everyone for…
GOVINDA Das: Thank you very much.